The fury of nature continues to draw the landscape of the Canary Islands.
The volcanic eruption has just occurred on the island of La Palma.
Opening windows to the interior of the earth.
How deep it is.
A fracture that was left open from the eruption, in which you can still see incandescence.
With lethal environments.
There is a triple concentration of CO2 in the air.
This can cause death in a matter of seconds.
Almost extraterrestrial.
Under the permanent threat of new eruptions.
What would happen if an eruption occurred in the Teide?
We would not exist without volcanoes.
We have to learn to live with them.
Canary Islands, Born of Fire.
Premieres Monday, September 12 at 10pm on National Geographic.