No scientist has enjoyed such global popularity.
She was the first to investigate the phenomenon of radioactivity
and discovered unknown radioactive elements for science.
She was the first woman to do her PhD at Sorbonne,
the first woman to win the Nobel Prize,
and the only one to receive the prestigious award twice.
Her name was Maria Słodowska-Kury.
She was born in Warsaw in 1867,
in the womb of a family dedicated to teaching.
The Słodowskis tried to instill in their five children
a love for knowledge.
Exact sciences were especially valued in that house.
At 16, Maria left the institute, graduating with a degree of honour.
In Poland, which at that time was part of the Russian Empire,
there were no institutions where women could continue to study,
and her family had no money to send their daughters to study abroad.
Then Maria proposed that her older sister should go to study in Paris,
and said that she would pay for her studies
by working as an institute teacher at a landlady's house.
Eight years later, Maria had saved enough money
to go to Paris to study at the University of Sorbonne.
She lived in a small village, where the heat was unbearable in summer,
and so cold in winter that the water froze in the washroom.
Maria lived on bread and tea,
but she had managed to study at the famous university,
and she made it her goal to dedicate her life to science.
While looking for a laboratory for her research,
the young 27-year-old Slodoska met Pierre Curie,
a well-known physicist.
They soon got married.
Their union, based on common points of view and interests,
turned out to be strong and harmonious.
Three years after the wedding, her first daughter, Irene, was born.
At the end of the 19th century,
important events took place in the field of physics.
In 1895, the German physicist Röntgen reported
that he had discovered a new type of penetrating rays,
later called X-rays.
A year later, the Frenchman Becquerel found out
that the minerals contained in uranium emitted
a powerful radiation of an unknown origin.
Slodoska Curie began to study that phenomenon
that should be called radioactivity.
Pierre joined his experiments,
leaving his own experiments with crystals.
In 1898, the Curie couple declared
that they had discovered two very radioactive elements.
Using the right given to her by being her discoverer,
Maria proposed that one of them be called Polonium,
in honor of her native Poland,
and the other one be called Radio.
However, discovering the existence of new elements
was not enough.
They had to be isolated.
To carry out the experiments,
the Curie couple obtained permission to use
a spare cover used in those days by medical students.
The experiments to isolate the radioactive elements
lasted for four years.
It is a tiring job, Maria Curie wrote.
You have to transport mineral bags,
pour solutions from one container to another,
stir the boiling liquid in a jar of molten iron for hours.
The titanic effort was crowned with success.
In 1902, scientists obtained
a decigram of pure radio chloride.
The appearance of that white powder
was similar to that of table salt,
but the light radiating from it was so bright
that it could be read near the tubes
in which the radio salt was stored.
Impressed by the extraordinary work of the physicists,
Vladimir Mayakovsky later compared
the process of obtaining radio with poetry.
You have to work a whole year to get a gram.
Despite its precarious nature,
the scientists did not patent their discoveries.
Marie said,
the radio should not enrich anyone.
This element belongs to the world.
For their work on radioactivity,
Marie and Pierre Curie were awarded
the Nobel Prize in Physics in 1903.
A year later, Eve, her second daughter, was born.
And two years later, in 1903,
Pierre Curie died rolled up by the wheels of a heavy cart.
The hard blow of fate
would not discourage Marie.
It happened to her husband in the physics class of the Sorbonne,
contributing to the creation of the Institute of Radio in Paris,
and was appointed director of the Radioactivity Laboratory.
In 1911, Marie Curie received her second Nobel Prize,
this time in chemistry.
During the war, Marie Curie was killed by a bomb.
During the war, Marie Curie was director
of the Department of Radiology of the Red Cross
and worked in field hospitals.
She learned to drive and, when necessary,
she was also a mechanic.
In her youth, she had endured the cold
that was in her lap.
Then she carried out laborious experiments
in a cover that was not suitable for a laboratory.
But it was her calm and determination that characterized her.
Marie Slodowska Curie died as a result
of the radiation received at 66 years old.
The radioactive rays she investigated throughout her life
managed to undermine her health,
causing a leukemia that would have caused her death.
The most advantaged students of Marie Curie
were her eldest daughter Irene and Frédéric Joliot Curie,
who were awarded the Nobel Prize in 1935
for their discovery of artificial radioactivity.